{
  "reference_number": "184",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "The coalition government must set a target for 2050 in legislation now."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "The most ambitious target is reducing total greenhouse gases to net zero by 2050. The last election saw Maori turn out to support\n the Labour political party and help to return them to govern the nation. The obvious conclusion is that Maori prefer the direction of\n\n Labour’s policies under the new Prime Minister."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions (including from new forest planting) and using some emissions reductions from overseas (international carbon units) that have strong environmental safeguards",
      "answer_index": 2,
      "notes": "By using only domestic emissions reductions as well as including information for the new forest planting being promoted by the\n\n Honourable Shane Jones."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The 2050 target should not be altered in response to market place as this undermines the certainty of the Act. However, the ability to\n revise the 2050 target in light of major changes in scientific and Indigenous understandings or international agreements should be\n\n considered."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I agree with 5-year budgets set 10-15 years in advance so that 3 are in effect at all times."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "No - emissions budgets should not be able to be changed",
      "answer_index": 9,
      "notes": "The proposed emissions budgets should not be altered in response to the market as this undermines their certainty. However, the\n\n ability to revise budgets in light of major changes in scientific and Indigenous understandings or international agreements should be\n considered."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "The 2050 target should not be altered in response to market place as this undermines the certainty of the Act. However, the ability to\nrevise the 2050 target in light of major changes in scientific and Indigenous understandings or international agreements should be\n\nconsidered."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "I agree that the coalition government and the climate commission should take the following factors into consideration when advising\n\non and setting budgets: Indigenous Maori knowledge and [western] science."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes, the coalition government must learn from their own mistakes as well as international mistakes; for example, the mistake of the\n\nUK's Climate Change Act and specify a strict time frame for producing a plan."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The government’s policy plans to meet emission budgets must be environmentally sustainable and should reflect a commitment to\nthe Treaty of Waitangi (Article 3, at least), the theory of partnership and the spirit of the Treaty, and UNDrip. Otherwise, the plan would\n\nrequire the government to re-define the Maori treaty rights which would leave intact individual property rights, unrestrained\nexploitation of resources, maximisation of private profit, and the supreme authority of the prevailing state."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "The Climate Change Commission must not be the decision-making body."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": "The Commission should advise the coalition government on policy settings in the NZ ETS."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I agree that collective expertise and wisdom is essential and desirable. Begin by respecting the human rights of the original\nprotectors of the land. Indigenous Maori people have been at the forefront of protecting the rivers, coasts, forests and lands from\n\nout-of-control industrial activity. The coalition government is able to strengthen this role and reset our relationship by implementing, at\nleast, Article 3 of the Treaty of Waitangi, the theory of partnership and spirit of the Treaty, and the United Nations Declaration on the\n\nRights of Indigenous Peoples. The development of a Zero Carbon Bill must draw on the wisdom that, “(i)f you wouldn’t want it in your\nbackyard, then it doesn’t belong in anyone’s backyard” (Kline, N. 2017)."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes. This will require an adaptation [Maori] sub-committee within the Climate Commission."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I would agree if the Indigenous Maori people’s ideas and lived experience was supported."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "nil"
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "While the global economic model is failing the vast majority of people on the planet, it is not failing all of the people the same. I want to\n\nrecommend that the coalition government considers UNDRIP and the Treaty of Waitangi and that a Zero Carbon Act adequately\nengages the human rights issues that arise from the fossil-fuel industry; that is, the right to clean air to breathe and clean water to\n\ndrink, now and for generations to come."
    }
  ]
}
